Guide to the Matthew Arnold Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Matthew Arnold collection
1825-1939
1850-1888
GEN MSS 867
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.29
(6 boxes)
The Matthew Arnold Collection is a mixed-provenance collection of material by and related to Matthew Arnold, including family, personal and professional correspondence; diaries by Mary Penrose Arnold; letters from Frances Lucy Arnold to Arthur Galton; and a small quanitity of personal papers and manuscript items. Correspondents include Arthur Hugh Clough, James Thomas Knowles and George Smith.
Arnold, Matthew, 1822-1888
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by gift and purchase from various sources between 1928 and 2005, as noted on individual folders or on the catalog cards included with the collection.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Matthew Arnold (1822-1888)
Matthew Arnold (1822-1888), son of British educator Thomas Arnold, was a poet and critic who began his education at Rugby School, where his father was headmaster. In 1841, he entered Balliol College, Oxford, where he began his life-long friendship with the poet Arthur Hugh Clough, graduating in 1844. In 1851, through the patronage of Lord Lansdowne, he was appointed one of Her Majesty's Inspectors of Schools, a position he held until his retirement in 1883. He married Frances Lucy Wightman, Lord Lansdowne's daughter, in the same year. The Arnolds had six children, only three of whom survived to adulthood.
Much of Arnold's poetry was written by the time Arnold turned thirty. His major collections include The Strayed Reveller and Other Poems (1849); Empedocles on Etna and other Poems (1852); Poems by Matthew Arnold (1853, 1854, 1857); and New Poems (1867). He is perhaps best known today for the elegaic Dover Beach and Stanzas from the Grande Chartreuse. Arnold's literary and cultural criticism included the highly influential Culture and Anarchy (1869) and other collections of critical essays, many of which first appeared in periodicals such as Cornhill Magazine and The Athenaeum. In addtion, he published two works on French and Continental schools.
Arnold retired from the civil service in 1883 on a pension secured for him by William Gladstone. He made two extensive lecture tours of the United States, in 1883 and 1886. Matthew Arnold died of a sudden heart attack in Liverpool on April 15, 1888, and was buried three days later beside his children at Laleham.
Scope and Contents
The Matthew Arnold Collection is a mixed-provenance collection of material by and related to Matthew Arnold, including family, personal and professional correspondence; diaries by Mary Penrose Arnold; letters from Frances Lucy Arnold to Arthur Galton; and a small quanitity of personal papers and manuscript items.
Series I, Matthew Arnold Letters and Other Papers, contains letters by Matthew Arnold to family members, friends and professional colleagues. Major recipients include his close friend, the poet Arthur Hugh Clough; James Thomas Knowles, the editor first of the Contemporary Review and then of The Nineteenth Century; and George Smith, the founder of Cornhill Magazine. An 1834 letter to Martha Buckland is written partially in verse. The series also contains an autograph manuscript of George Sand and notes and documents relating to Arnold's career as an Inspector of Schools.
Series II, Mary Penrose Arnold Diaries, contains the personal diaries of Arnold's mother for the years 1825 to 1842, while Series III, Frances Lucy Arnold Correspondence, consists entirely of letters from Frances Arnold to the Reverend Arthur Galton.
Series IV, the Fred Whitridge Collection of Arnold Family Papers, consists almost entirely of correspondence inherited or gathered by Frederick Whitridge, a grandson of Matthew Arnold. Contents include several folders of letters from Arnold to his daughter Lucy Arnold Whitridge, as well as letters to his mother and his sister Fan; letters to Arnold from a variety of correspondents, including Benjamin Jowett, Sir Henry Irving, Thomas Henry Huxley, and John Henry, Cardinal Newman; and a notebook on theater and notes in Arnold's hand.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Matthew Arnold Letters and Other Papers, 1845-1888. II. Mary Penrose Arnold Diaries, 1825-1842. III. Frances Lucy Arnold Correspondence, 1885-1920. IV. Fred Whitridge Collection of Arnold Family Papers, 1849-1939.
Authors and publishers -- Great Britain; Authors, English -- 19th century -- Archives; English literature -- 19th century; English poetry -- 19th century; Great Britain -- Intellectual life -- 19th century; Diaries -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Arnold family; Arnold, Frances Lucy; Arnold, Mary Penrose, 1791-1873; Arnold, Matthew, 1822-1888; Arnold, Thomas, 1795-1842; Clough, Arthur Hugh, 1819-1861; Galton, Arthur, 1852-1921; Knowles, James, Sir, 1831-1908; Smith, George, 1824-1901
- Matthew Arnold Letters and Other Papers, 1845-1888; Series I; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  The series is alphabetically arranged.
  Scope and Contents
  The series consists almost entirely of letters by Matthew Arnold. Major recipients include Arthur Hugh Clough, James Thomas Knowles, and George Smith. Also included are an autograph manuscript of George Sand and autograph notes taken by Arnold as Inspector of Schools.
  - Catalog cards, undated; 2 (Box 1)
  - Letter: to Mr. Aitchison, no year September 27 (Box 1)
  - 5 letters: to Charles Edward Cutts Birch Appleton, 1872-1879 (Box 1)
  - 2 letters: to Thomas Arnold (brother), 1860, 1864 (Box 1)
  - Letter: to William Thomas Arnold ("Willy"), 1881 September 3 (Box 1)
    Tinker 122
  - Letter: to Mr. Bourne, 1874 May 5 (Box 1)
  - Letter: to Martha Buckland, 1836 May 14 (Box 1)
    The first page of the letter is in verse by Matthew Arnold.
    Letter annotated by Thomas Arnold (father).
  - Letter: to Mssrs. Burr of Hartford, Connecticut, [1883] November 15 (Box 1)
  - Letter: to Lord Carlingford, no year June 30 (Box 1)
    Recipient is Chichester Samuel Parkinson-Fortescue, Baron Carlingford, 1823-1898.
  - 54 letters: to Arthur Hugh Clough, 1845-1861; 62 (Box 1)
    With: 5 letters to Mrs. Arthur Hugh Clough, 1861-1868; 1 letter from Charles T. Penrose to Matthew Arnold, 1861 March 25; a note in Arnold's hand, undated; and a copy of Arnold and Clough, 1933 January 12.
  - Letter: to Mrs. Cumberledge, 1888 February 27 (Box 1)
    Tipped to dated autograph of Matthew Arnold.
  - Letter: to Mrs. Earle, no year July 27 (Box 1)
  - Letter: to Julian Fane, undated (Box 1)
    Letter dated: "Easter Monday."
  - Letter: to Sir Joshua Fitch, 1880 October 5 (Box 1)
  - 4 letters: to Mrs. Eduardo Nicolà Fusco, 1874-1875, undated (Box 1)
    3 letters in French.
  - 5 letters: to Sir Arthur Helps, 1868-1871, undated (Box 1)
  - Letter: to E. Lloyd Jones, 1883 January 26 (Box 1)
  - Letter: to Sir James Kay-Shuttleworth, 1867 March 19 (Box 1)
    Incomplete and damaged.
  - 31 letters: to James Thomas Knowles, 1869-1879, undated; 3 (Box 1)
  - Letter: to Sir James Lacaita, 1876 July 18 (Box 2)
  - Letter: to Alexander Macmillan, 1869 February 25 (Box 2)
  - Letter: to Mrs. Bryant Morgan, 1884 January 8 (Box 2)
  - Letter (in the 3rd person): to John Murray, 1871 April 20 (Box 2)
  - 3 letters: to Charles Myhill, 1885 (Box 2)
    Accompanied by: photograph of National Gallery portrait of Arnold
  - Letter: to Mr. Ruault, no year February 17 (Box 2)
  - Letter: to Miss St. John, 1870 January 14 (Box 2)
  - Letter: to Horace Seymour, [1881] September 25 (Box 2)
  - 2 letters: to Mrs. Shand, undated (Box 2)
  - 30 letters: to George Smith, 1865-1874; 3 (Box 2)
  - Letter: to Miss Smith, 1867 June 10 (Box 2)
  - 5 letters: to Elizabeth Thompson, 1886, undated (Box 2)
  - 4 letters: to Henry Yates Thompson, 1884-1886, undated (Box 2)
  - Letter: to James Toovey, 1852 April 21 (Box 2)
  - Letter: to Arthur Williams, 1876 February 28 (Box 2)
  - Letter: to James Yoxall, [1880] April 23 (Box 2)
  - Letter: to "Bernard", 1868 October 28 (Box 2)
  - Letter: to "My dearest K", no year August 1 (Box 2)
  - Letter: to unidentified recipient, 1887 September 6 (Box 2)
  - Letter: to an unidentified recipient, undated (Box 2)
  - George Sand: autograph manuscript, corrected, signed, [1877] (Box 2)
    Presentation inscription: from John Morley to the Earl of Rosebery.
    Ex libris Earl of Rosebery.
  - Notes made in Arnold's capacity as Inspector of Schools, 1868-1871 (Box 2)
  - Photograph and portraits of Matthew Arnold, 1881, 1883, undated (Box 2)
  - Teacher's certificate issued to William Salmon, signed by Matthew Arnold and other school inspectors, 1865-1882 (Box Broadside 3)
    Accompanied by a photostat of a teacher's certificate issued to Rosella Pitman, signed by Matthew Arnold and other school inspectors.
    Accompanied by a copy of a portrait of Matthew Arnold.
- Diaries of Mary Penrose Arnold, 1825-1842; Series II; 0.42; (1 box)
  The series is chronologically arranged
  The series consists of the personal diaries kept by Mary Penrose Arnold between 1825 and 1842.
  - Diaries, 1825-1842; 11 (Box 4)
- Frances Lucy Arnold Correspondence, 1885-1920; Series III; 0.21; (1 box)
  The series is chronologically arranged.
  The series contains letters from Frances Lucy Arnold to the Reverend Arthur Galton, a family friend who was tutor to Frederic Manning.
  - Letters to Arthur Galton, 1885-1920; 10 (Box 5)
- Fred Whitridge Collection of Arnold Family Papers, 1849-1939; Series IV; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Organized into four subseries: Letters by Matthew Arnold; Letters to Matthew Arnold; Third-Party Correspondence; and Other Family Papers
  The series consists almost entirely of correspondence, including letters from Matthew Arnold to various family members, particularly his mother, his sister Fan, and his daughter Lucy; letters to Arnold from family members, friends and professional colleagues; and a letter from William Wordsworth to John Kenyon. There is also one folder of Arnold family papers, including a notebook on theater productions in Arnold's hand.
  - Letters by Matthew Arnold
    - Letters to Mary Penrose Arnold (mother), 1859-1872, undated; 3 (Box 5)
    - Letters to Fan Arnold (sister), 1860-1884, undated; 2 (Box 5)
    - Letters to Jane Martha Arnold ("K"; sister), 1849-1887, undated (Box 5)
    - Letters to Frances Lucy Arnold ("Flu"; wife), 1879, undated (Box 5)
    - Letter to Alfred Austen, 1887 December 18 (Box 5)
    - Letters to Susanna Arnold Cropper ("Susy"; sister), 1865-1886, undated (Box 5)
    - Typescript copies of letters (1849-1888) to Tom Arnold (brother), undated (Box 5)
    - Letters to Lucy Arnold Whitridge (daughter), 1854-1887, undated; 5 (Box 5)
    - Letter to Mr. Zincher, 1883 January 27 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous and unidentified family letters, 1849-1887, undated (Box 5)
  - Letters to Matthew Arnold
    - Arnold family "round robin" letters, 1831, undated (Box 6)
    - Arnold, Mary Penrose, 1831 (Box 6)
    - Arnold, Thomas, 1831 September 20 (Box 6)
    - Bailey, Philip James, 1877 November 16 (Box 6)
    - Bourget, P., 1887 (Box 6)
      In French.
    - Cobden, Richard, 1864 (Box 6)
    - Coleridge, John Duke, 1863 December 12 (Box 6)
    - Derby, Edward Henry Stanley, Earl of, 1882 September 24 (Box 6)
    - Du Maurier, George, 1876 November (Box 6)
    - Froude, J. A., undated (Box 6)
    - Granville, Granville George Leveson-Gower, Earl, 1864 June 27 (Box 6)
    - Grey, Henry George, Earl, 1884 March 11 (Box 6)
    - Guizot, M. (François), 1859 March (Box 6)
    - Harcourt, William Vernon, Sir, 1882 July 2 (Box 6)
    - Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1853-1875 (Box 6)
    - Irving, Henry, Sir, 1873 June 2 (Box 6)
    - Jowett, Benjamin, 1888 January 9 (Box 6)
    - Lansdowne, Lord, undated (Box 6)
    - Leighton of Stretton, Frederick Leighton, Baron, undated (Box 6)
    - Lytton, Edward Bulwer-Lytton, Baron, 1867-1869 (Box 6)
    - MacDonald, George, 1872 March 24 (Box 6)
    - Macmillan, Alexander, 1878-1888 (Box 6)
    - Manchester, William Montague, Duke of, undated (Box 6)
    - Morley, John, 1886, 1890 (Box 6)
    - Newman, John Henry, 1871-1872 (Box 6)
    - Nisand, Alexis, undated (Box 6)
    - Räss, Andres, 1859 January 26 (Box 6)
    - Richmond, George, 1855 July 15 (Box 6)
    - Rosebery, Archibald Philip Primrose, Earl of, 1884-1888 (Box 6)
    - Salisbury, Robert Cecil, Marquess of, 1870 June 1 (Box 6)
    - Sargent, Nicolas-Marie, Bishop of Quimper, 1859 (Box 6)
    - Smith, W. H., 1882 March 16 (Box 6)
    - Stephen, James Fitzjames, 1859 January 25 (Box 6)
    - Temple, Frederick, 1865, 1867 (Box 6)
    - Trébutien, G. S. (Guillaume Stanislas), 1863 March 3 (Box 6)
    - Unidentified, 1859-1883, undated (Box 6)
  - Third-Party Correspondence
    - Fletcher, Eliza to Thomas Arnold, 1852 November 5 (Box 6)
    - Wightman, "Aunt" to Miss Wightman, undated (Box 6)
    - Wordsworth, William to John Kenyon, 1833 September 23 (Box 6)
      With an autograph manuscript copy of To Lowther Castle.
  - Other Arnold Family Papers, 1850-1939
    - Notebook concerning theater productions, undated (Box 6)
    - Notes and quotations, undated (Box 6)
    - Poetry, 1850-1881, undated (Box 6)
      Includes printed copies of Geist's Grave and Saint Brandan.
    - Correspondence and research files concerning Arnold Whitridge's research on Arnold, 1935-1939, undated; 2 (Box 6)